<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Young Rewired State 2015</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/blog/young-rewired-state-2015/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/blog/young-rewired-state-2015/</id>
    <published>2015-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-05-06T21:21:49+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I hosted a &lt;a href="http://yrs.io/"&gt;Young Rewired State&lt;/a&gt; group at &lt;a href="https://www.lostmy.name"&gt;Lostmy.name&lt;/a&gt;, where a group of youngsters (Donald, Saul and Theo) joined us for a week to design and build a prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They made &lt;a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20150912205139/http://hacks.youngrewiredstate.org/events/festival-of-code-2015/ko-llect"&gt;Kollect&lt;/a&gt;, an application for local businesses to share their surplus food with people in need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch them present their pitch in style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe class="youtube" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/X00LET30gLM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Leaving the BBC</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/blog/leaving-the-bbc/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/blog/leaving-the-bbc/</id>
    <published>2013-01-14T09:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-05-06T21:21:49+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I joined the BBC as a software engineer in Future Media for Audio &amp;amp; Music Interactive just over 5 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was just before &lt;a href="http://derivadow.com/2007/10/18/programme-support/"&gt;the first release&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes"&gt;BBC Programmes&lt;/a&gt;, and it was a couple of months before the &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer"&gt;iPlayer&lt;/a&gt; streaming service on the web launched in December 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to the BBC because having developed a number of research prototypes in academia for a few years, I wanted to build stuff with a significant number of real users. And I’ve certainly been able to do that, having worked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on a page for each artist on &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/music"&gt;BBC Music&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b01pfbjw#segments"&gt;clickable tracklists for programmes pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a year at &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio1/"&gt;Radio 1&lt;/a&gt; working on things like the &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio1/chart/singles"&gt;chart&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio1/livelounge/"&gt;live lounge&lt;/a&gt; and getting &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/radio/2011/02/using_twitter_to_control_a_slot-car_race_mistajam_vs_scott_mills.html"&gt;twitter to drive Scaletrix cars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on the &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/bbcinternet/2011/09/radio1_homepage_software_technical.html"&gt;Radio 1/1Xtra homepage&lt;/a&gt; project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on a &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio1/bigweekend/2010/"&gt;number&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/music/festivals/glastonbury/2011/"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/music/festivals/readingandleeds/2011/"&gt;events&lt;/a&gt; sites, both in the good old static html days and with the new &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/e9wmxj"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/events/edvg9r"&gt;events&lt;/a&gt; platform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;on &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/bbcinternet/2012/10/introducing_bbc_iplayer_radio.html"&gt;the launch&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio/"&gt;iPlayer Radio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been incredible. I’ve learnt so much, not just from the technical side but also as an individual. I’ve worked with really brilliant developers, designers and editorial - making great friends along the way. I’ve worked on some amazing projects, and written code that is used by millions of users each week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, all good things must come to an end and I’ve decided it’s time for me to move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday was the last day at the BBC for me, and today I’m starting as a technical lead at &lt;a href="http://www.sidekickstudios.net"&gt;Sidekick Studios&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Screecha - our Music Hack Day 2012 project</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/blog/screecha-our-music-hack-day-2012-project/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/blog/screecha-our-music-hack-day-2012-project/</id>
    <published>2012-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-05-06T21:21:49+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last weekend I participated in another &lt;a href="http://london.musichackday.org/2012/index.php?page=Main+page"&gt;Music Hack Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to convince &lt;a href="http://www.kirstenfletcher.com/"&gt;Kirsten Fletcher&lt;/a&gt;, to join me. Kirsten is a freelance costume designer-maker, who is more used to working on theatre and movie productions than hack days.
## Screecha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together we made &lt;a href="https://www.hackerleague.org/hackathons/music-hack-day-london/hacks/screecha"&gt;Screecha: an interactive musical toy aimed at children&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a puppet that can house a smart phone in it’s belly and an app to go with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the app, children can:
- listen to their favourite songs (using the &lt;a href="https://developer.spotify.com/technologies/web-api/"&gt;Spotify Metadata API&lt;/a&gt; and Cocoalibspotify)
- view the lyrics as the song plays (using &lt;a href="http://developer.echonest.com/"&gt;Echonest&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://musixmatch.com/"&gt;Musixmatch&lt;/a&gt;)
- record their own songs and upload them to &lt;a href="http://soundcloud.com"&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;
- listen to the masterpieces they’ve previously uploaded to SoundCloud&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a song plays, the puppet can be manipulated to sing along with the music.
## The idea&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea was mostly inspired by hanging out with some close friends who have a baby. They were talking about how many children’s songs and nursery rhymes were available on Spotify, which led us to think about a Spotify app as a physical toy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then started looking on other music services for children’s songs and came across a recording of a toddler singing &lt;a href="https://soundcloud.com/micheletharp/twinkle-twinkle-little-star"&gt;“Twinkle, Twinkle Little Star” on SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;. That’s when we decided that the ability of recording and saving children’s performances would add an interesting angle to the hack.
## Hacking with a sewing machine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/sewing_machine.jpeg" alt="Screecha - our Music Hack Day 2012 project" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was was doing the usual coding activities involved in a hack day (basically throwing code together until it worked), Kirsten designed and built the puppet from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obviously required a fair bit of planning and organisation upfront. She had to have an idea of what the puppet would look like in order to select which materials she’d need to bring to the hack day. She had to bring in her sewing machine (the first sewing machine at a Music Hack Day!) and a big bag of fabric as well as the other tools required to make the puppet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/pattern_cutting.jpeg" alt="Screecha - our Music Hack Day 2012 project" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was really interesting to see the process that she took. Based on a simple sketch for the design, she created a pattern: a paper template from which she made the preliminary shape for the puppet. After some tweaking, she adjusted the pattern and cut the fabric for the final puppet prototype. Then it was a matter of sewing it all together and finishing it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It really made me appreciate how lucky software and web developers have it: all we need is a laptop and internet connection and we’re effectively limited by our imagination and ability.
## Hacking with iOS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/screecha_sceenshot.jpg" alt="Screecha - our Music Hack Day 2012 project" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Screecha app was actually the first time I developed a native iOS application. It was implemented using PhoneGap, so most of the user interface was developed using HTML/CSS/Javascript and Twitter Bootstrap. However, I did have to integrate &lt;a href="https://github.com/spotify/cocoalibspotify"&gt;cocoalibspotify&lt;/a&gt; so I did get to tinker about with some Objective C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Hackday prototype, it was actually a bit disappointing to have developed a proof of concept that couldn’t be shared or made publicly accessible. If I had to do it again, I think I would go down the mobile webapp route using the HTML5 Audio API.
## Focus&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the start, we had a really clear idea of what we wanted to build: a puppet and a simple app that allowed you to play music, record sounds and upload them to SoundCloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We focused on implementing just that, resisting the temptation to add more features to the app or consider hacking some hardware into the puppet - there simply wouldn’t have been enough time to complete the prototype otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, good hacks can be the result of lots of iteration, last minute changes and a great deal of “hacking”. With Screecha, we took a good idea and focused on implementing just the essential features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Screecha won an award from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SpotifyPlatform/status/270232939898494977"&gt;Spotify for best use of the Spotify API&lt;/a&gt;, and an award from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SoundCloudAPI/status/270216164297306112"&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Buy a brick </title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/blog/buy-a-brick/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/blog/buy-a-brick/</id>
    <published>2012-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-05-06T21:21:49+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/buyabrick.png" alt="Buy a brick " /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago I helped develop a fundraising application for the &lt;a href="http://www.childsifoundation.org/"&gt;Child’s i Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, a charity and worldwide community aiming to build a home for abandoned babies in Uganda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time the charity was raising money to set up a home in Kampala, so the team at Childsi came up with &lt;a href="http://buyabrick.childsifoundation.org/"&gt;Buy a Brick&lt;/a&gt;, a web app where users donate from £2.50 to £500 to purchase a brick to build a virtual wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2 years since it launched, the Child’s i Foundation community has bought nearly 400 bricks, raised nearly £18,000!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I implemented the backend of the application in Ruby on Rails, in particular the integration with the payment gateway for processing donations. It was the first (and only) e-commerce website that I’ve ever deployed and maintained - I learnt a lot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple of weeks,  we’ve been tinkering with the application so it uses the &lt;a href="http://apimanagement.justgiving.com/"&gt;Just Giving&lt;/a&gt; donations API instead of the original payment gateway. We ended up using (and &lt;a href="https://github.com/mintdigital/just_giving/pull/1"&gt;patching&lt;/a&gt;) the &lt;a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/just_giving/"&gt;Just Giving Ruby gem&lt;/a&gt;, so the switch over was pretty simple to implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What wasn’t so simple was upgrading an old, pre-Bundler Rails 2.2 application to Rails 2.3 and getting the right combination of gems versions to play together on Heroku! But I got there in the end…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application is at &lt;a href="http://buyabrick.childsifoundation.org/"&gt;buyabrick.childsifoundation.org/&lt;/a&gt; and the code is all on Github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/childsi/buyabrick/"&gt;github.com/childsi/buyabrick/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The new BBC Radio 1 and 1Xtra homepages</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/blog/the-new-radio-1-and-1xtra-homepages/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/blog/the-new-radio-1-and-1xtra-homepages/</id>
    <published>2011-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-05-06T21:21:49+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, Radio 1 and 1Xtra launched their new homepages:
- &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio1/"&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio1/&lt;/a&gt;
- &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/1xtra/"&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/1xtra/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/bbcinternet/2011/09/radio1_homepage_software_technical.html"&gt;written a “under-the-hood” post on the BBC Internet blog&lt;/a&gt;, describing how we approached the technical challenges to meet the editorial ambitions for the new homepage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was on attachment with the Radio 1 and 1Xtra Interactive team when the design was conceived, and although the site was built by the &lt;a href="http://www.madebykite.com"&gt;fantastic team at Kite&lt;/a&gt; I’ve been heavily involved throughout it’s development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/BBC_-_Radio_1_20110930.png" alt="The new BBC Radio 1 and 1Xtra homepages" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might be a bit biased, but I think it’s pretty special! What I’m most happy with is how we’re pushing content to the page using &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/blogs/radiolabs/2009/11/pushfeeds.shtml"&gt;BBC PushFeeds&lt;/a&gt; (i.e. &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/about-xmpp/technology-overview/pubsub/"&gt;XMPP PubSub&lt;/a&gt; over &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebSocket"&gt;Websockets&lt;/a&gt; or Flash as a fallback) to enable the live experience. On top of that, we’ve delivered an admin system that allows producers to promote content to the homepages within seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/BBC_-_Radio_1Xtra_20111005.png" alt="The new BBC Radio 1 and 1Xtra homepages" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Track now playing information has been present on the BBC national radio networks sites for a number of years, but in the new homepage they are put into the spotlight. The beautiful packshots (album art) are mainly taken from the Radio 1/1Xtra charts and playlists.  Using &lt;a href="http://musicbrainz.org/"&gt;MusicBrainz&lt;/a&gt; identifiers we’re able to surface content from &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/music"&gt;BBC Music&lt;/a&gt;, including artist biography, latest clips and album reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/image003_570.jpg" alt="The new BBC Radio 1 and 1Xtra homepages" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this reinvents the way the stations present themselves online, and potentially on air. Whenever something happens in the studio, it’s on the website in seconds in the form of an update, photo or live video stream. The audience’s reaction to the show can be surfaced online in the form of their texts, tweets or Facebook comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s opened up a new toy box of possibilities, and I’m really looking forwards to see how both the audience and the stations engage with what we’ve built.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Young Rewired State 2011</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/blog/young-rewired-state-2011/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/blog/young-rewired-state-2011/</id>
    <published>2011-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-05-06T21:21:49+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I took part in &lt;a href="http://youngrewiredstate.org/"&gt;Young Rewired State&lt;/a&gt; (YRS), a week long hack event aimed at young developers aged between 15 and 18 and focused around Open Data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/cholten99"&gt;Dave&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/kerron"&gt;Kerron&lt;/a&gt;, I was one of the mentors at the Young Rewired Blackfriars which was hosted at &lt;a href="http://fluxx.uk.com/"&gt;Fluxx Studios&lt;/a&gt;. Our group started by brainstorming during the first morning, focusing on 4/5 ideas which eventually led to 1 project: searching and visualising University course data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team built &lt;a href="http://youngrewiredstate.org/projects/unimatch/"&gt;UniMatch&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/unimatch.png" alt="Young Rewired State 2011" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a live demonstration available at &lt;a href="http://unimatch.net/"&gt;http://unimatch.net/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really impressed by the &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/yrsblackfriars"&gt;Fluxx Capacitors&lt;/a&gt; team. I loved the way they came up with ideas during the brainstorming sessions - there was some really great things coming out of it. Coding wise, there was a wide range of abilities, from those who had been programming for years (i.e. since they were 10), some of them had tinkered with some HTML and CSS and others who hadn’t coded at all but were keen to learn. The more experienced ended up doing the heavy lifting on the server side and more advanced Javascript front end work, and the rest of them worked on designing the UI and then implementing the design and HTML/CSS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/photo.JPG" alt="Young Rewired State 2011" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some really ingenious approaches to working collaboratively too. When they started editing the code on a shared server space, they used a system consisting of wooden blocks for each of the components (e.g. HTML, CSS, database and server code) to prevent multiple people editing the same file at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a mentor, it was brilliant to be able to point the more code-oriented people in the right way in terms of software development best practices such as source code control and web applications frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t able to attend the presentation, but it’s available on the &lt;a href="http://www.ustream.tv/channel/yrs2011"&gt;YRS UStream channel&lt;/a&gt;. They did a fantastic pitch (&lt;a href="http://www.ustream.tv/recorded/16449306"&gt;about 1h 9m mins in&lt;/a&gt;), and came away with the &lt;em&gt;Most likely to be bought (code or concept)&lt;/em&gt; prize. Great work Leon, Richard, Joanne, Hugo, Kerron and Priscilla!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of them are continuing to work on the project, so it’ll be interesting to see what they come up with.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
